NYSUT Biography File 6174/019
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT Biography File
1961-1975
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT)
6174/019
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Articles, news clippings, photographs.
7899496
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, November 07, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, November 07, 2014
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA- NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Scope and Contents
Biographies of officers and field staff of New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) 1961-1975. Includes some photographs (formal head shots), many in poor condition.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: All other 6174 collections
Teachers' union, New York (State); New York State United Teachers; New York State United Teachers. Archives
7899496
- Anderson, George E., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Photo and press release from New York State Teachers' Association announcing appointment of Anderson as administrative assistant and business manager; newspaper clipping announcing appointment, 1968
- Bain, Helen P., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Photo and biographical sketch of president of National Education Association
- Barrett, Catherine, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Formal photos and negative; resume of Barrett as president of New York State Teachers Association and a director of National Education Association, 1969, and as vice president/president elect of NEA, 1971-72; biographical sketches
- Barry, Franklyn S., 1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Photo and background information re president of New York State Teachers Association
- Bovard, Robert C., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Photo and resume of NYSTA field representative; newspaper clipping of biography in NYSTA News Trends
- Bush, Ronald W. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Biographical information and newspaper clipping of NYSTA field representative
- Cantor, Arnold (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Photo
- Crawford, Ronald C., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Photo and resume; press release from NYSTA announcing appointment of Crawford as regional services representative
- Cummings, R. Elaine (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Resume
- D'Angelo, John (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Photo; resume, c. 1971
- Freedman, Ira, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Photo and negative; background information and resume as assistant in public relations for NYSTA
- Gimbernat, Ruth (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Photo; newspaper clipping as new associate editor of New York State Education; biography as administrative assistant for NYSTA Long Island Regional Office
- Goold, G. Howard, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Photos of Goold as a young man and later in life; resume; clipping from Who's Who in American Education, 1967-68, and Who's Who in the East, 1972-73, as executive secretary of NYSTA
- Harvey, John J. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Resume of NYSTA public relations coordinator for Western New York; resume of wife Christine Frances Harvey
- Hill, Norman, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Newspaper clipping from New York Teacher, "Norman Hill Succeeds Bayard Rustin as Director of Randolph Institute," with biographical information, January 19, 1975
- Hopkins, Ned K. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Resume and press release from NYSTA re appointment of Hopkins as director of public relations, c. 1970
- Howard, Richard C. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Kerr, Blanche W. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Photo, 1957; resume
- Knapp, John R., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Photo; NYSTA press release re appointment of Knapp as instruction intern; resume
- Kraus, Harry N., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Resume of NYSTA director of public relations
- Kullman, Nathan E., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Photos and negative; resume of assistant executive secretary, NYSTA
- Lambert, Sam M. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Photos of executive secretary of NEA
- Law, Kenneth L., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Leggio, Edward J. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- MacDonald, Helene Conroy (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Photos and negative
- Manners, Robert C. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Photos; resume
- Matterson, Curtiss B., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Photos; biographical information for NYSTA field representative
- McKillip, Daniel C., 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Clippings from NYTSA News Trends re field representative
- McLaughlin, Arthur F., Jr., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Photo negatives; biographical information
- Paliwodzinski, Robert L. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Photo; resume
- Rowley, Richard R., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Clippings from NYSTA News Trends announcing the designation of law firm Sneeringer and Rowley as counsel to NYSTA, with biographical description of Rowley
- Rustin, Bayard, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Biography of Bayard Rustin, executive director/president of the A. Philip Randolph Institute; newspaper clipping from New York Teacher announcing replacement of Rustin as executive director by Norman Hill, 1975
- Selden, David, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Biography of David Selden, president of American Federation of Teachers, AFL-CIO
- Trobridge, Rex Charles (Box 1, Folder 34)
  Resume, c. 1974
- Vincent, Florence (Box 1, Folder 35)
  Photos
- Walters, Marguerite J. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Photos; resume of NYSTA director of professional services
- White, Francis J., Jr. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  Resume of executive secretary of NYSTA; photos
- Wilson, Lois (Box 1, Folder 38)
  NYSTA press release announcing appointment of Lois Wilson as director of studies